Inventory of the Charles Curtiss papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Charles Curtiss papers
1938-1987
87036
Curtiss, Charles, 1908-
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives
Correspondence, writings, notes, minutes, reports, resolutions, and printed matter, relating to internal divisions within the Mexican section of the Fourth International, Fourth International activities elsewhere, relations between Leon Trotsky and Diego Rivera, and theoretical debates in Trotskyist and social democratic circles.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1987.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
American Trotskyist and subsequently socialist; Fourth International representative, Mexico, 1938-1939.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, writings, notes, minutes, reports, resolutions, and printed matter, relating to internal divisions within the Mexican section of the Fourth International, Fourth International activities elsewhere, relations between Leon Trotsky and Diego Rivera, and theoretical debates in Trotskyist and social democratic circles.
Fourth International; Rivera, Diego, 1886-1957.; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940.; Communism--Mexico.; Communism--United States; Socialism--United States.
- "Documents and Records of a Representative of the Fourth International In Mexico" created and collected by Charles Curtiss, 1938-1940
  - "Reorganizing the Mexican Section of the Fourth International,", 1939 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - "The Break with Diego Rivera,", 1938-1940 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - "Plenum of the National Committee" minutes, 1938 Nov. 19-20 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - "Pan-American (Latin American, etc.) Bureau of the IV International" minutes, 1938 Nov 8 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - "Documents of the Fouth International and its affiliates and individuals in Europe and Latin America,", 1938-1941 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Alexander, Robert J. (Professor of Rutgers University on Mexican Section of the Fourth International) correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Allen, Naomi (Pathfinder Press) correspondence, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - "An appraisal of Leon Trotsky," undated (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - "Diego Rivera's Stand of 48 Years Ago Debated,", 1986-1987 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - "Notes on the history of labor in Mexico since the overthrow of Porfirio Diaz, especially on Partido Liberal Mexicano and the Flores Magon brothers; articles and writings on the Alianza Popular Revolucionaria Americana (APRA),", 1908-1921 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - "Leon Trotsky and the Mexico of Cardenas, 50th Anniversary, Days of Commemoration,", 1987 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Articles from various periodicals on socialist democracy, dictatorship of the proletariat, and Leninism, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 1: 12)